Guide to the Chapel Farm Records 1911-2008 (bulk, 2000-2003) MS 108
New-York Historical Society
Chapel Farm records
1911-2008 (bulk, 2000-2003)
New-York Historical Society
MS 108
1.29 Linear feet (3 boxes)
Chapel Farm is located in the Riverdale section of the Bronx. The area is a dense forest. This collection mostly contains the records of the efforts to save it from real estate developers from 1991-2003. The types of materials included in this collection are correspondence, maps, reports, appraisals, clippings, books, and legal documents.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in four series. Within each series the materials are arranged chronologically.
Series I: Chapel Farm Real Estate Development, 1911-2005
Series II: John Fitzgerald / Chapel Farm Estates, Inc. / Villanova Estates, 1984-2003
Series III: Opposition to Development, 1984-2002
Series IV: Environmental Material Not About Chapel Farm, 1923-2001
Historical Note
Chapel Farm is located in the Riverdale section of the Bronx, New York. The area is not actually a farm, but a forest. The property was originally a religious retreat built by the Griscom family, the founders of the Theosophical Society. Ludlow Griscom was the Chairman of the Board of Directors of the National Audubon Society for many years. In 1969 Chapel Farm was bought by Manhattan College to build dormitories, but used it as an environmental research station. Due to declining enrollment, Manhattan College started seeking a buyer. Over the next three decades many development plans were put forth, but never went through. One deal did proceed and the College sold five acres at the northern end of Chapel Farm to SGD Corporation. This sale included the lease of the "mansion", which is a house built by the Griscom family, for 99 years and a 99 year renewal. The current owner of Chapel Farm is Villanova Estates, a corporation owned by John Fitzgerald. Fitzgerald planned to build thirteen home sites in the Chapel Farm area. Local residents and politicians opposed the development of Chapel Farm including access/roads, blasting, drainage, tree removal, and erosion control. Fitzgerald eventually started building the homes in 2005.
Scope and Content Note
The records of Chapel Farm mainly consist of records to fight the development of the area by John Fitzgerald. There are limited records of previous fights against development. The issues covered in these papers include tree removal, erosion control, access/roads, blasting, and construction progress. The types of materials included in this collection are correspondence, maps, survey maps, environmental information, reports, statements of individuals and community groups, and legal information. Also included are two books, one about New York birds written by Ludlow Griscom and another about Ludlow Griscom. There is a gap in information from 1927 to 1955; the materials from 1911 to 1927 are maps and one book.
Materials added to the collection in 2008 are predominantly from Hilary Kitasei and Barbara Michael, and many are annotated in pencil in Ms. Michael's hand.
Agendas; Brochures.; Calendars.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Fliers (printed matter); Leases.; Maps.; Newsletters.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Reports.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- History -- 20th century.; Chapel Farm (Bronx, New York, N.Y.); Riverdale (New York, N.Y.); City planning -- New York (State) -- New York.; Forests and forestry -- New York (State) -- New York.; Greenbelts -- New York (State) -- New York.; Housing -- New York (State) -- New York.; Land use -- New York (State) -- New York.; Real estate development -- New York (State) -- New York.; Bronx Community Board No. 8; Fieldston Property Owners Association; New York Audubon Society; Fieldston Road Homeowners; Riverdale Nature Preservancy; Trust for Public Land (U.S.); Fitzgerald, John; Griscom, Ludlow, 1890-1959; Kitasei, Hilary
- Series I: Chapel Farm Real Estate Development, 1911-2005
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains material relating to the history of Chapel Farm and the real estate development projects that have been attempted over the years. Most pertain to the battle with John Fitzgerald. The types of materials included are correspondence, pamphlets, notes, legal information, reports, clippings, maps, and survey maps.
  - History, 1955, 1959, 1998, 2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Background information on environment of Chapel Farm, [2002], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Legal Documents: sale of lot, Land Trust, Environmental Control Board, and others, 1959, 1990, 2001-2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - CEQR Environmental Assessment Statement, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Lists of donors, potential donors, residents, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Maps of Chapel Farm and surrounding area, 1911, 1927, 2000-2001, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Survey maps of Chapel Farm, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Lot maps, property and construction photos (2008 donation), 2004-2008 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence to and from Riverdale residents regarding Chapel Farm, 1977-2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1969-2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper clippings (2008 donation), 1997, 2001-2007 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Series II: John Fitzgerald / Chapel Farm Estates, Inc. / Villanova Estates, 1984-2003
  This series contains materials from and to John Fitzgerald and his associates. The types of materials included are correspondence, leases, statements of findings, reports, maps, and plans.
  - Correspondence, 1984-2003, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Legal and planning materials, 1986-2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series III: Opposition to Development, 1984-2002
  The materials included in this series are organized into two subseries: community (Subseries 1) and city and state organizations (Subseries 2) opposed to the development of Chapel Farm. The types of materials included are correspondence, reports, newsletters, statements, agendas, statements of opposition, calendars, publications, conservation plans, and a map.
  - Subseries 1: Community Organizations
    The materials included in the subseries are from community organizations opposed to the real estate development of Chapel Farm. The types of materials included are correspondence, reports, newsletters, statements, and a map.
    - Fieldston Property Owners Association, 1984-2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Fieldston Property Owners Association, 2001, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Fieldston Road Homeowners, 2000-2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Riverdale Nature Preservancy, 1991-2002, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Riverdale Nature Preservancy, Chapel Farm Task Force, 2001-2003 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Community Board No. 2, 1985-2001 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Trust for Public Land, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Environmental organizations, 1995-2001 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Environmental organizations, 2001-2002, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Riverdale Community Association, Wave Hill, Jewish Board of Family and Children's Services, Inc., 2001 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 2: New York City and New York State Organizations
    The materials included in the subseries are from state and city organizations, most of which were opposed to developing Chapel Farm into real estate. The materials include correspondence, agendas, statements of opposition, calendars, publications, lists, and conservation plans.
    - Bronx Borough President, 2001, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - New York City Planning Commission, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Parks Council, 1983-2002, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - New York City Council, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - New York State information, 2001-2002, Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Series IV: Environmental Material Not About Chapel Farm, 1923-2001
  This series includes environmental information pertaining not to Chapel Farm but to areas that are similar. Also included are two books, one about Ludlow Griscom and one written by him. The types of materials included are diagrams, birding information, flyers, brochures, photos, and plans.
  - Environmental information on trees, rain, and birds, Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Fliers, pamphlets, and plans of other parks and preserves, 1992, 1997, 2001, Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Books: Dean of the Bird Watchers: A Biography of Ludlow Griscom, Birds of the New York City Region, 1923, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Photos of ropes course, Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)